Finding Aid for University of Michigan admissions lawsuits collection, 1995-2003
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
University of Michigan admissions lawsuits collection 1995-2003
University of Michigan.
2 CD-ROMs
27 linear feet
0264 Bimu 2
Two lawsuits filed in 1997 (Gratz, et al. v. Bollinger; and Grutter, et al. v. Bollinger) made the University of Michigan a focal point in the national debate over the value and legality of affirmative action in higher education. The lawsuits brought by non-minority applicants challenged the legality of the university's admissions process. Documentation includes briefs, judicial orders and opinions, expert reports, trial transcripts and exhibits, and amicus briefs from companies and organizations supporting the university's position in both the Gratz and Grutter case. Also included are snapshot of the university's admissions lawsuits website and clippings and media files.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group (donor no. 4094 ) was received from the Office of the General Counsel in January 2002. Additional material was received from the Vice President for Communications in September 2003. Additional material was received from the Vice President for Communications in September 2003. A second accession from the Office of the General Counsel was received in June 2008.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open without restriction.
Two lawsuits filed in 1997 alleging that the University of Michigan's admissions practices discriminated against non-minority applicants made the university a focal point in the contentious national debate over the value and legality of affirmative action in higher education. In response to the filings in U.S. District Court, University President Lee Bollinger declared that in challenging the university's consideration of race as a positive factor in admissions, the lawsuits attacked a policy "deeply rooted in the history, traditions and the identity of the University," and a common practice among the nation's leading institutions of higher education. While President Bollinger and other members of the university community conducted a highly visible national media campaign to explain and elicit support for the university's admissions policies and the values upon which they were based, the lawsuits also stimulated intense discussion on the University of Michigan campus over issues of diversity, fairness, and equal opportunity.
On October 13, 1997, Jennifer Gratz, an unsuccessful white applicant for the Fall 1995 term, and Patrick Hamacher, an unsuccessful white applicant for the Fall 1997 term, brought a lawsuit in district court against the College of Literature, Science and the Arts (LS&A). On December 3, 1997, Barbara Grutter, an unsuccessful white applicant for the Fall 1997 entering class, brought a similar suit against the Law School. The plaintiffs sued both the university and specific university officials, including President Lee Bollinger, President Emeritus James Duderstadt, and Law School Dean Jeffrey Lehman, in their individual and official capacities. Both cases were certified as class actions for purposes of reviewing the policies at issue.
The Center for Individual Rights (CIR), a nonprofit public interest law firm located in Washington, D.C., represented the plaintiffs, with the Minneapolis law firm of Maslon, Edelman, Borman, & Brand serving as lead counsel. The CIR had been active in conducting lawsuits seeking to dismantle affirmative action in college admissions and racial preference in a variety of arenas, including a successful case against the University of Texas Law School (Hopwood v. State of Texas). The university's lead counsel for the suits was John Payton, a civil rights attorney of the Washington D.C. law firm of Wilmer, Cutler & Pickering, with local counsel provided by Butzel Long of Detroit.
The plaintiffs in the cases charged that the university unlawfully discriminated against them by taking race and ethnicity into account as a positive factor in admissions. They sought injunctive relief and monetary damages. The university took the position that the Constitution and civil rights statutes, as interpreted by the Supreme Court in its 1978 decision in the case of University of California v. Bakke, permitted it to consider race and ethnicity in its admissions in order to achieve the educational benefits of a diverse student body. (The Bakke decision stated that there must be a "compelling governmental interest" to justify the use of race in admissions. The university asserted that diversity was just such an interest.)
In both lawsuits, groups of students and citizens petitioned to intervene in support of the university's admissions policy. Although their intervention was initially denied by the district courts, in August 1999 the U.S. Court of Appeals for the Sixth Circuit allowed the intervention and made the student and citizen groups full parties in the case. The intervenors defended the university's policy on the basis that it was needed to remedy past and/or present discrimination against people of color. In the LS&A case, the intervenors included 17 African-American and Latino students who applied or planned to apply to the university and the group Citizens for Affirmative Action Preservation. In the Law School case, the intervenors included 41 students and three groups: United for Equality and Affirmative Action, the Coalition to Defend Affirmative Action By Any Means Necessary, and Law Students for Affirmative Action.
Many organizations and entities filed "friend of the Court" (amicus) briefs in the Court of Appeals for both sides of the case. Organizations filing briefs in support of the university's position included General Motors Corporation, the American Bar Association, the American Council on Education, the National Organization for Women (NOW) Legal Defense Fund, the Attorney General of Michigan, and a group of Fortune 500 companies including Microsoft, Intel, Pfizer, and others. Organizations filing amicus briefs in support of the plaintiffs included the National Association of Scholars.
On December 13, 2000, Judge Patrick Duggan ruled without a trial and granted summary judgment in the university's favor in the Gratz case. Finding that the pursuit of the educational benefits of diversity is a compelling governmental interest, he ruled that the university's current admissions policy, in place since 1999, was fully constitutional, but that its admissions policy from 1995 to 1998 was unconstitutional. In a separate opinion, Duggan rejected the intervenors' alternative argument defending the policy. CIR has petitioned to appeal the judgment about the current admissions process and the university has petitioned to cross-appeal the ruling on the unconstitutionality of the admissions process for the years 1995 to 1998.
From January 16 through February 16, 2001, a limited trial on the specifics of the Law School admissions process was held. On March 27, 2001, Judge Bernard Friedman issued a decision for Grutter finding that the educational benefits of diversity were not a compelling interest, and that the specifics of the Law School's policy were not "narrowly tailored" to that interest. He also struck down the intervenors' defense, saying that it was essentially based on remedying societal discrimination and impermissible. He issued an order that the Law School cease considering race in its admissions process. The university immediately appealed the ruling and filed a motion for a stay of injunction. On April 5, 2001, the Court of Appeals issued a stay of the District Court order, allowing the Law School to continue using its current admissions policy while the appeal proceeds.
In October 2001, the Sixth Circuit Court of Appeals granted the plaintiffs' motion for hearing oral arguments en banc. The hearings were scheduled for December 2001. In May 2002 the Sixth Circuit Court of Appeals held in the Grutter case that the Law School's admissions policy is constitutional, reversing the March 27, 2001 decision of Judge Friedman. From August 2002 to October 2002 petitions for certiorari, asking the U.S. Supreme Court to view the Grutter and Gratz case were filed. In December 2002 the U.S. Supreme Court granted certiorari before judgment on the Constitutional issue only in Gratz and granted certiorari in the Grutter case. Oral arguments were heard before the U.S. Supreme Court in Gratz and Grutter on April 1, 2003. A decision from the U.S. Supreme Court was delivered on June 23, 2003. In a 5-4 vote, the U.S. Supreme Court justices upheld the University of Michigan Law School admissions policy (Grutter v. Bollinger, et. al) and in a 6-3 vote struck down the university's undergraduate admissions policy (Gratz and Hamacher v. Bollinger, et. al). On July 18, 2003, the plaintiff in Grutter v. Bollinger et al. filed a petition with the U.S. Supreme Court requesting to rehear the case. The petition for rehearing of Grutter was denied on August 25, 2003.
Following the Supreme Court's 2003 decision in Gratz, the case was returned to the U.S. District Court for the Eastern District of Michigan for further proceedings. In August 2003, the University Michigan Office of Undergraduate Admissions announced a new process for reviewing student applications that included more individualized review. This process was in place for those students applying for admissions for the Fall 2004 term.
On January 31, 2007, in an agreement reached between the parties and approved by the District Court, the plaintiffs in the case agreed to forego damages, and drop all claims in the lawsuit in return for $10,000 each to cover costs. Although the defendants agreed to payment for costs, there was no finding that the university's pre-2003 admissions policy caused injury to the plaintiffs.
The records are organized in four series, Grutter v. Bollinger, et al., Gratz v. Bollinger, et al., Admissions Lawsuits Website and News Media. The first three series contain briefs, judicial orders and opinions, experts' reports, amicus briefs from companies and organizations supporting the university's position in the lawsuits, and a limited number of press releases and documents printed from the website maintained by the university's News and Information Services regarding the lawsuits. The News Media series, however, is entirely comprised of news articles, editorials and press releases from newspapers across the country. Note that the record group currently contains only public documents. It does not contain internal General Counsel documents or correspondence regarding the lawsuits.
Subjects:
Multicultural education.; Affirmative action programs--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Universities and colleges--Admission--Law and legislation--United States.; Discrimination in education--Law and legislation--United States.; University of Michigan--Trials, litigation, etc.
Genre Terms:
CD-ROMs.
- Grutter v. Bollinger, et al. 1997-2001
  The Grutter v. Bollinger, et al. series, 1997-2001 (15 linear feet) was received in two accessions. In addition to the materials found in both series, this first accession (boxes 1-13) includes trial transcripts and trial exhibits. The series also includes two videotapes, one of major television news coverage of the 2001 decision in the case from NBC News, CNN, ABC, and MSNBC and another of a 2000 feature about the lawsuits from 60 Minutes.
  The second accession of Grutter v. Bollinger records, (2 linear feet, boxes 20-21), consists of the twelve-volume Joint Appendix for Grutter, filed on the case's appeal from the United States District Court for the Eastern District of Michigan to the Sixth Circuit Court of Appeals.
  - Plaintiff's Motion for Partial Summary Judgment on Liability 1999 (Box 1)
  - Plaintiff's Memorandum of Law in Support of Motion for Partial Summary Judgment 1999 (Box 1)
  - Defendants' Memorandum of Law in Support of Motion for Summary Judgment 1999 (Box 2)
  - Appendix in Support of Defendants' Motion for Summary Judgment 1999
    - Documents and Materials (Box 2)
    - Deposition Excerpts (Box 2)
    - Expert Witness Reports (Box 2)
  - Defendants' Motion for Summary Judgment 2000 (Box 3)
  - Defendants' Memorandum of Law in Support of Renewed Motion for Summary Judgment and Appendix 2000 (Box 3)
  - Appendix in Support of Defendants' Renewed Motion for Summary Judgment on Grounds of Qualified Immunity 2000 (Box 3)
  - Plaintiff's Memorandum in Opposition to Renewed Motion for Summary Judgment on Grounds of Qualified Immunity 2000 (Box 3)
  - Plaintiff's Expert Reports 1-8 1998-2001 (Box 4)
  - Defendants' Expert Reports 1998-2001
    - 1-6 (Box 4)
    - 7-15 (Box 4)
  - Intervenors' Expert Reports 1999-2001 (Box 5)
    - 1-5 (Box 5)
    - 6-10 (Box 5)
    - 11-15 (Box 5)
  - Trial Transcripts (Box 6)
    - Volume 1
      - January 16, 2001 (Box 6)
      - January 17, 2001 (Box 6)
      - January 18, 2001 (Box 6)
      - January 19, 2001 (Box 6)
    - Volume 2
      - January 22, 2001 (Box 6)
      - January 23, 2001 (Box 6)
      - January 24, 2001 (Box 6)
  - Miniscript Trial Transcripts 2001 (Box 6)
  - Trial Exhibits 2001, 12 volumes (Box 7)
    - volumes 1-3 (Box 7)
  - Trial Exhibits 2001 (cont.)
    - volumes 4-7 (Box 8)
    - volumes 8-10 (Box 9)
    - volumes 11-12 (Box 10)
  - Supplemental Trial Exhibits 2001 (Box 10)
  - District Court Amicus Briefs-Gratz and Grutter 2000, 2 volumes (Box 11)
    - American Council on Education (Gratz & Grutter) (Box 11)
    - Association of American Law Schools, et al.(Gratz) (Box 11)
    - Attorney General (Gratz & Grutter) (Box 11)
    - College Board (Gratz) (Box 11)
    - General Motors (Box 11)
    - Law Students (Grutter) (Box 11)
    - Memorandum of Law in the issue of Summary Judgment (Grutter) (Box 11)
    - "Me Too" (Gratz & Grutter) (Box 11)
    - Motion of Attorney General Jennifer Granholm (Gratz) (Box 11)
    - National Association of Scholars (Gratz & Grutter) (Box 11)
    - State of Ohio (Gratz & Grutter) (Box 11)
    - United States (Gratz & Grutter) (Box 11)
  - Final Briefs 2001
    - Final Brief of Appellee July 27, 2001 (Box 11)
    - Final Brief of Defendants-Appellants July 27, 2001 (Box 11)
    - Final Reply Brief of Defendants-Appellants July 27, 2001 (Box 11)
    - Final Brief of Defendants-Appellees July 27, 2001 (Box 11)
    - Final Reply Brief of Defendant-Intervenors July 27, 2001 (Box 11)
    - Final Brief of Defendant-Intervenors July 27, 2001 (Box 11)
  - Court of Appeals (Box 12)
    - Amicus Briefs 2001, 2 volumes
      - International Union, United Automobile, Aerospace & Agricultural Implement Workers of America (Box 12)
      - Civil Rights Project at Harvard University (Box 12)
      - NOW Legal Defense and Education Fund (Box 12)
      - Honorable John Conyers, Jr., the Honorable Carolyn Cheeks Kilpatrick, the Honorable Kwame M. Kilpatrick, the Honorable Dennis Archers, and Saul Green, Esq. (Box 12)
      - American Council on Education, et al. (Box 12)
      - Michigan Attorney General (Box 12)
      - Judith Areen, Katherine Bartlett, Robert Clark, Michael Fitts, Anthony Kornman, David Leebron, John Sexton, and Lee Teitelbaum (Box 12)
      - General Motors Corporation (Box 12)
      - 3M, Abbott Laboratories, et al. (Box 12)
      - Ohio State University and the Ohio State University College of Law (Box 12)
      - Lawyers' Committee for Civil Rights Under Law (Box 12)
      - 36 Individual Faculty Members of the Ohio State University College of Law (Box 12)
      - Clinical Legal Education Association (Box 12)
      - National Asian Pacific American Bar Association, et al. (Box 12)
      - American Bar Association (Box 12)
    - Proof Briefs of Plaintiffs, Defendants, and Intervenors 2001
      - Proof Brief of Defendants-Appellants May 24, 2001 (Box 12)
      - Proof Brief of Defendant-Intervenors-Appellees June 4, 2001 (Box 12)
      - Proof Brief of Plaintiffs-Appellees June 15, 2001 (Box 12)
      - Proof Brief of Defendant-Appellees June 15, 2001 (Box 12)
      - Proof Reply Brief of Defendants-Appellants June 25, 2001 (Box 12)
  - Expert Report of Walter R. Allen 1997 (Box 13)
  - Plaintiffs' Complaint December 3, 1997 (Box 13)
  - Defendants' Answer December 3, 1997 (Box 13)
  - Proposed Intervening Defendants' Motion to Intervene March 26, 1998 (Box 13)
  - Memorandum of Law in Support of Motion to Intervene March 26, 1998 (Box 13)
  - Reply Memorandum of Proposed Intervening Defendants March 26, 1998 (Box 13)
  - Plaintiffs' Memorandum in Opposition to Motion for Intervention April 22, 1998 (Box 13)
  - University's Response to Motion to Intervene April 23, 1998 (Box 13)
  - Opinion and Order Denying Motion to Intervene July 6, 1998 (Box 13)
  - Plaintiffs' Motion for Class Certification and for Bifurcation of Liability and Damages Trials July 30, 1998 (Box 13)
  - Memorandum of Law in Support of Plaintiffs' Motion for Class Certification and Bifurcation July 30, 1998 (Box 13)
  - Defendants' Opposition to Plaintiffs' Motion to Certify a Class Action and to Bifurcate Liability from Damages September 10, 1998 (Box 13)
  - Opinion and Order Granting Plaintiffs' Motion for Class Certification and Bifurcation January 7, 1999 (Box 13)
  - Sixth Circuit Ruling Allowing Intervention August 10, 1999 (Box 13)
  - Amicus Brief Filed by Fortune 500 Corporations October 16, 2000 (Box 13)
  - Transcript of Closing Arguments at Trial February 16, 2001 (Box 13)
  - Defendants' Post-Trial Brief February 26, 2001 (Box 13)
  - Opinion Granting Defendants' Motion for Stay of Injunction Pending Appeal April 5, 2001 (Box 13)
  - Proof Brief of Defendants-Appellants May 16, 2001 (Box 13)
  - Final Reply Brief of Defendants-Appellees July 27, 2001 (Box 13)
  - Final Brief of Defendants-Appellees July 27, 2001 (Box 13)
  - Defendant-Intervenors' Final Brief July 26, 2001 (Box 13)
  - Defendant-Intervenors' Final Reply Brief July 26, 2001 (Box 13)
  - Defendant-Intervenors-Appellees' Final Brief July 26, 2001 (Box 13)
  - Major Television News Coverage of Ruling 2001 (VHS videotape) (Box 13)
  - 60 Minutes, October 25, 2000 (VHS videotape) (Box 13)
  - On Appeal from the United States District Court for the Eastern District of Michigan, Sixth Circuit Appeal, Joint Appendix July 13, 2001 (Box 20)
    Volumes 1-11
  - On Appeal from the United States District Court for the Eastern District of Michigan, Sixth Circuit Appeal, Joint Appendix July 13, 2001 (Box 21)
    Volumes 12-21
- Gratz v. Bollinger, et al., 1997-2007
  The first accession of The Gratz v. Bollinger, et al. series, 1997-2001 (4 feet, boxes 14-17) is comprised mainly of court documents and expert reports. Additional materials in the Gratz and Hamacher v. Bollinger, et al. received in 2008, (4 linear feet, boxes 22-26), further document the university's actions in the case and include legal petitions, motions, and memoranda; experts' reports; amici briefs; and judicial decisions and opinions, including those regarding the case settlement and dismissal.
  - Summary Judgment 1999 (Box 14)
    - Plaintiffs' Pleadings with Appendices
      - Plaintiffs' Motion for Partial Summary Judgment on Liability April 7, 1999 (Box 14)
      - Plaintiffs' Memorandum of Law in Support of Motion for Partial Summary Judgment on Liability April 8, 1999
        - Affidavit and Exhibits (Volume I of II) in Support of Plaintiffs' Motion for Partial Summary Judgment on Liability (Box 14)
        - Affidavit of Kirk O. Kolbo in Support of Plaintiffs' Motion for Partial Summary Judgment on Liability April 7, 1999 (Box 14)
        - Affidavit and Exhibits (Volume II of II) in Support of Plaintiffs' Motion for Partial Summary Judgment on Liability (Box 14)
      - Plaintiffs' Memorandum in Opposition to Defendants' Motion for Summary Judgment and Reply Memorandum in Support of Plaintiffs' Motion for Partial Summary Judgment May 30, 1999
        - Affidavit of Kirk O. Kolbo and Exhibits Submitted in Plaintiffs' Opposition to Defendants' Motion for Summary Judgment February 9, 1999 (Box 14)
    - Defendants' Motion and Documents and Materials
      - Defendants' Motion for Summary Judgment April 29, 1999 (Box 14)
      - Defendants' Opposition to Plaintiffs' Motion for Partial Summary Judgment and Memorandum in Support of Defendants' Cross-Motion for Summary Judgment May 3, 1999
        - Defendants' Appendix Vol. 2-Deposition Excerpts (Box 14)
  - Plaintiffs' Expert Reports 1-8 1998-2000 (Box 15)
    - Geshekter January 22, 1999 (Box 15)
    - Heriot August 29, 2000 (Box 15)
    - Larntz
      - December 14, 1998 (Box 15)
      - August 27, 1999 (Box 15)
      - August 3, 2000 (Box 15)
      - September 11, 2000 (Box 15)
      - October 28, 2000 (Box 15)
    - Welch May 26, 2000 (Box 15)
  - Defendants' Expert Reports 1-13 1998-2000
    - Bowen December 9, 1998 (Box 15)
    - Camara August 8, 2000 (Box 15)
    - Camarillo December 14, 1998 (Box 15)
    - Foner December 15, 1998 (Box 15)
    - Gurin
      - December 15, 1998 (Box 15)
      - July 13, 2000 (Box 15)
    - Raudenbush
      - January 22, 1999 (Box 15)
      - March 3, 1999 (Box 15)
      - February 24, 2000 (Box 15)
      - July 13, 2000 (Box 15)
      - October 26, 2000 (Box 15)
    - Steele December 14, 1998 (Box 15)
    - Sugrue December 15, 1998 (Box 15)
  - Intervenors' Expert Reports 1-6 1999-2000
    - Allen July 6, 2000 (Box 15)
    - Allen & Solrzano October 11, 2000 (Box 15)
    - Anderson June, 2000 (Box 15)
    - Feagin June 13, 2000 (Box 15)
    - Silver & Rudolph June 13, 2000 (Box 15)
    - Trent June 17, 2000 (Box 15)
  - Appeals Court Amicus Briefs 2001, 2 volumes (Box 16)
    - General Motors (Box 16)
    - Steelcase, et al. (Box 16)
    - American Council on Education, et al. (Box 16)
    - NOW Legal Defense and Education Fund (Box 16)
    - Harvard Civil Rights Project (Box 16)
    - Lawyers Committee for Civil Rights Under Law (Box 16)
    - Ohio State University, et al. (Box 16)
    - Stanford Institute for Higher Education Research (Box 16)
    - International Union, United Automobile, Aerospace & Agricultural Implement Workers of America (Box 16)
    - 36 Individual Faculty Members of OSU College of Law (Box 16)
    - Pacific Legal Foundation (in support of Plaintiffs) (Box 16)
    - Southeastern Legal Foundation (in support of Plaintiffs) (Box 16)
    - National Association of Scholars (in support of Plaintiffs) (Box 16)
    - National Capital Association of Scholars, Maryland Association of Scholars, and Virginia Association of Scholars (in support of Plaintiffs) (Box 16)
  - Appeals Court Briefs-Plaintiffs, Defendants, Intervenors 2001
    - Proof Brief of Plaintiffs-Appellants and Appellees May 7, 2001 (Box 16)
    - Proof Brief for Defendant-Intervenors/Appellants May 14, 2001 (Box 16)
    - Proof Brief of Defendant-Appellees and Appellants June 5, 2001 (Box 16)
    - Proof Brief of Defendant-Intervenors-Appellees June 6, 2001 (Box 16)
    - Proof Brief of Defendants-Appellees June 13, 2001 (Box 16)
    - Proof Brief of Plaintiffs-Appellees June 30, 2001 (Box 16)
    - Reply Brief of Plaintiffs-Appellants and Appellees June 27, 2001 (Box 16)
    - Proof Reply Brief for Defendant-Intervenors/Appellants June 27, 2001 (Box 16)
  - Plaintiffs' Complaint October 14, 1997 (Box 17)
  - University's Answer December 3, 1997 (Box 17)
  - Motion to Intervene February 5, 1998 (Box 17)
  - Memorandum of Law in Support of Motion to Intervene February 5, 1998 (Box 17)
  - Proposed Answer of Intervening Defendants February 5, 1998 (Box 17)
  - Plaintiffs' Memorandum in Opposition to Motion to Intervene February 22, 1998 (Box 17)
  - Response to First Amended Motion to Intervene February 24, 1998 (Box 17)
  - Order of Judge Duggan Denying Motion to Intervene July 7, 1998 (Box 17)
  - Opinion of Judge Duggan Denying Motion to Intervene July 7, 1998 (Box 17)